Guide to the Ellen McGowan Biddle Shipman papers, 1914-1946.
Shipman, Ellen McGowan Biddle papers, 1914-1946.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Ellen McGowan Biddle Shipman papers, 1914-1946.
1259
Ellen McGowan Biddle, Shipman 1869-1950.
25.6 cubic ft.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Correspondence, bills, orders, vouchers, subject files on landscaping and garden ornamentation, lectures, articles, printed material, a broadside. Photographs, planting plans, and oversize drawings and blueprints of gardens and landscape designs by Ellen Shipman.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Born in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania in 1869 to General James Biddle and the former Ellen McGowen, Ellen McGowen Shipman went on to become one of the leading landscape architects of the first half of the 20th Century. Shipman left Radcliff after one year and married Louis Shipman an aspiring playwright. The two lived for a time in Plainfield, New Hampshire near the Cornish Artist Colony that had grown up around the sculptor Augstus Saint-Gaudens. It was here that Shipman was influenced by a group of artist gardeners and also where she would meet the landscape architect Charles Adams Platt. After her marriage dissolved in 1910, Shipman went on to collaborate with Platt for a number of years, eventually creating her own practice and moving to Beekman Place in New York City in 1920. While the 1920s were the busiest for Shipman, with commissions decreasing dramatically in the depression years of the 1930s, Shipman would design gardens from her townhouse overlooking the East River for the next 30 years. The majority of her designs were done in the English style but she is most noted for her use of "painting" the landscape with plants and flowers as well as her use of border plantings to create a sense of private space. It is unfortunate that since many of her commissions were for grand estates and her plantings particularly labor intensive to maintain, many had disappeared within her own lifetime and very few of have survived to the present day. Examples of her existing gardens include the Edison and Ford Winter Estate in Fort, Myers, Florida and Stan Hywet Hall in Akron, Ohio. Ellen McGown Shipman died in March, 1950.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Correspondence, bills, orders, vouchers, subject files on landscaping and garden ornamentation, lectures, articles, printed material, a broadside. Photographs, planting plans, and oversize drawings and blueprints of gardens and landscape designs by Ellen Shipman.
Also material regarding the Lord and Schryver: Shaping our Cultural Landscape exhibit in 2011 at the Hallie Ford Museum of Art.
Also Angell, Nicholas B. (June 1, 2011) “Letter No. 3, The Young Ellen Biddle Shipman, our Grandmother, and her Family, 1863-1893.” Copy of a letter to his grandchildren, grandnieces and grandnephews from Nicholas Biddle Angell, EBS’s grandson (son of her daughter, Mrs. Montgomery Angell), about the Biddle family and her early life. Has 14 pages of text, plus 10 un-numbered pages of scanned photographs, including those of the young EBS. #1259m in Box 34.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Shipman, Ellen McGowan Biddle,1869-1950.
Subjects:
Garden ornaments and furniture.; Gardens.; Landscape architecture.; Landscape gardening.; Landscape architects.; Women landscape architects.
Form and Genre Terms:
Blueprints.; Architectural drawings.; Broadsides.; Drawings.; Lectures.; Photographs.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Access Restrictions:
Contents of Mapcase Folder 195 require permission of the Shelburne Museum, Shelburne, VT to copy.
SERIES LIST
Series I. Photographs
Boxes 1-7, 12-17
Series II. Correspondence
Boxes 8-10
Series III. Articles, Manuscripts, and Printed Materials
Boxes 10-11, 18; Map Case Folder 196, Map Case Item 1
General
Notes and Drafts for an Unpublished Book
Posters
Series IV. Project Files
Map Case Folders 1-201; Map Case Items 2-17
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Photographs (Prints and Negatives)
  - Arranged by Client
  - Achelis, Frederick G. (Box 1, Folder 1-4)
  - Aetna Life Insurance Company (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Location: Hartford, Connecticut
  - Alger, Frederick (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Location: Grosse Pointe, Michigan
  - Alger Russell (Box 1, Folder 7-13)
    York Harbor, Maine
    Photo by Thomas Ellison
  - Alger Russell (Box 15)
    Photo by Thomas Ellison (matted)
  - Allen, Frederick (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Allen, J. Roy (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Allington, Courtenay (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Atkinson (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Barbour, Edwin S. (Box 1, Folder 18-19)
  - Black, Durel (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Blair, McCormick (Box 1, Folder 21-24)
    Location: Lake Bluff, Illinois
  - Brady, James C. (Box 1, Folder 25-27)
  - Brewer, Robert S. (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Brown, Horace (Box 1, Folder 29-32)
    Location: North Mowing, Springfield, Vermont
  - Bulkley, Jonathan (Box 1, Folder 33)
    Location: "Rippowam", Ridgefield, Connecticut
  - Burke, E.S. Jr. (Box 1, Folder 34-36)
    Location: Chagrin Falls, Ohio
  - "Chatham" (Mrs. Devore) (Box 1, Folder 37-38)
    Location: Fredricksburg, Virginia
  - Clapp, Willard (Box 1, Folder 39-46)
    Location: Cleveland, Ohio
    Photos by Thomas Ellison
  - Cooper, James Fenimore (Box 2, Folder 1-11)
    Location: Cooperstown, New York
    Photos by Slote Studio
  - Croft, Henry (Box 2, Folder 12-13)
    Location: Greenwich, Connecticut
  - Croft, Henry (Box 15)
    Photo by Mattie Edwards Hewitt (matted)
  - Daniels, Alanson L. (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Location: Wenham, Massachusetts
  - Daniels, Alanson L. (Box 15)
    Photo by Edith Hastings Tracy (matted)
  - Davis, T.B. (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Location: Middleburg, Virginia
  - deWaal, Christian (Box 2, Folder 16-18)
    Location: Lexington, Kentucky
  - Dillman, Mr. and Mrs. Hugh (Box 2, Folder 19-22)
    Photos by Preston H. Sweet
  - Dillman (Dodge), Mr. and Mrs. Hugh (Box 15)
    Photos by Preston H. Sweet (matted)
  - DuPont, Eugene (Box 2, Folder 23-25)
    Location: Greenville (Centerville), Delaware
  - Dyer, Lyman T. (Box 2, Folder 26-28)
    Location: Oxford, New Hampshire
  - Emmons, R.W. (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Fahnestock, William (Box 2, Folder 30-32)
    Location: Katonah, New York
    Photos by Jessie Tarbox Beals
  - Fahnestock, William (Box 15)
  - Fish, Julia (Box 2, Folder 33-34)
    Location: Greenport, Long Island, New York
  - Fish, Julia (Box 15)
  - Ford, Henry (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Frank(s), Robert (Box 2, Folder 36-40)
    Location: Llewellyn Park, New Jersey
  - Gibson, Mary (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Godley, George McM. " Long House" (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Goldsmith (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Gossler, Philip (Box 3, Folder 2-5)
  - Greenough, Henry (Box 3, Folder 6-8)
    Location: Brookline, Massachusetts
    Photos by Dorothy Jarvis Studio
  - Hale, Robert (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Hall, Stan Hywett (Box 16)
    Location: Akron, Ohio
    Photos by Carol Betsch (matted)
  - Hanes, James (Box 3, Folder 10-11)
  - Hanes, Ralph (Box 3, Folder 12-15)
    Location: Winston-Salem, North Carolina
  - Hanson (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Harris, Julian (Box 3, Folder 17-18)
    Location: Nantucket, Massachusetts
  - Haskell (Box 3, Folder 19-20)
  - Hickox (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Hill, Francis, Powell (Box 3, Folder 22-23)
  - Hinks, R.S. (Box 3, Folder 24-25)
  - Holt (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Hopkins, Alfred (Box 3, Folder 27-28)
    Location: Princeton, New Jersey
  - Hoya, Eva (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Humphrey, George (Box 3, Folder 30)
    Location: Mentor, Ohio
  - Huntington (Box 3, Folder 31-33)
  - Ingalls, David (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Iselin, C. Oliver (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Jackson (Box 3, Folder 36-37)
  - Kenefick, T.S. (Box 3, Folder 38-39)
  - King, F.P. (Box 3, Folder 40-44)
    Location: Irvington, Kentucky
  - Kinnicutt (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Knox, S. (Box 3, Folder 46)
    Location: Ailsen, South Carolina
  - Kramer (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Lord, Franklin (Box 3, Folder 48)
    Location: Syosset, Long Island, New York
  - Lord, George (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Lord, John N. (Box 3, Folder 50-51)
  - Lowe (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Lowe, Edward (Box 3, Folder 53)
    Location: Grand Rapids, Michigan
    Photo by Mattie Edwards Hewitt
  - Lowe, Edward (Box 16)
  - Magee, John (Box 4, Folder 1-3)
    Location: Mount Kisco, New York
  - Magee, John (Box 16)
  - McGinley, Holden (Box 4, Folder 4-7)
    Location: Mattapan, Massachusetts
    Photos by Herbert W. Gleason
  - McGinley, Holden (Box 16)
    Photos by Herbert W. Gleason (matted)
  - McGraw, Sears (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - McGraw, Theodore (Box 4, Folder 9-18)
  - Martin, D. MD (Emma) (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Meriden Bird Club (Box 4, Folder 20-21)
  - Merrill, R.D. (Box 4, Folder 22-24)
  - Mitchell, Ormsby (Box 4, Folder 25-28)
    Photos by Harry G. Healy
  - Mitchell, Ormsby (Box 16)
    Photos by Harry G. Healy (matted)
  - Morris, Samuel (Box 4, Folder 29-31)
    Location: Philadelphia, Pennsylvania
  - Murphy, Fred T. (Box 4, Folder 32-37)
  - Neff, Richard (Box 4, Folder 38-45)
    Location: Houston, Texas
  - Newberry, John S. (Box 5, Folder 1-4)
    Photos by George W. Hance
  - O'Brien (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Parker, William A. (Box 5, Folder 6)
    Location: North Easton, Massachusetts
  - Parmelee, James (Box 5, Folder 7-10)
    Location: Washington, D.C.
    Photos by Frances B. Johnston
  - Peabody, Julian (Box 5, Folder 11)
    Location: Westbury, Long Island, New York
  - Peters, Henry T. (Box 5, Folder 12-13)
    Location: Islip, Long Island, New York
  - Pratt, Francis (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Preston, W.T. (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Proctor, F. (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Pruyn, Mary (Box 5, Folder 17)
    Location: East Hampton, Long Island, New York
  - Pruyn, Mary (Box 16)
  - Reed, Lansing (Box 5, Folder 18-20)
    Location: Cold Spring Harbor, New York
  - Reese (Box 5, Folder 21-22)
    Location: New Hamburg on Hudson, New York
  - Robertson, N.G. (Box 5, Folder 23-26)
  - Sales, Murray (Box 5, Folder 27-31)
    Photos by George G. Hance
  - Sales, Murray (Box 17)
    Photos by George G. Hance (matted)
  - Salvage, Samuel (Box 5, Folder 32-41)
    Location: Manhasset, Long Island, New York
  - Salvage, Samuel (Box 17)
  - Sanders Memorial (Box 5, Folder 42-43)
  - Sanford, Ferris (Box 5, Folder 44-45)
  - Schiff, Jacob (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Schley, Evander B. (Box 5, Folder 47-49)
    Location: Far Hills, New Jersey
    Photos by John Wallace Giles
  - Schley, Evander B. (Box 17)
  - Schley, Reeve (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Schlotman (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - Shipman, Ellen ("Brook Place') (Box 17)
    Location: Rutland, Vermont
  - Shoemaker, M.M. (Box 5, Folder 52)
    Location: Bennington, Vermont
  - Smith, Angus (Box 5, Folder 53-54)
  - Smith, Henry (Box 5, Folder 55)
    Location: Bay City, Michigan
  - Smith, Howard (Box 5, Folder 56-57)
  - Smith, William Watson (Box 5, Folder 58-61)
    Location: Lingonier, Pennsylvania
  - Spaulding, Samuel Strong (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
    Location: Springfield, Massachusetts
  - St. John's Parish House (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Starr, Isaac (Box 6, Folder 4-6)
    Location: Wyncote, Pennsylvania
  - Stern, Edgar B. (Box 6, Folder 7-15)
    Location: New Orleans, Louisiana
  - Stern, Edgar B. (Box 17)
    Photo by Shipman Office (matted)
  - Stranahan, R. (Box 6, Folder 16-18)
    Location: Ottowa Hills, Ohio
  - Strubing, Philip (Box 6, Folder 19-20)
    Location: Chestnut Hill, Pennsylvania
  - Swayne Red House (Box 6, Folder 21-22)
  - Takin (?), Herbert (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Thomas, James A. (Box 6, Folder 24)
    Location: White Plains, New York
  - Tucker Carll (Box 6, Folder 25-33)
    Location: Mt. Kisco, New York
  - Tucker Carll (Box 17)
  - Vanderbilt, R.T. (Box 6, Folder 34)
    Location: Greens Farm, Connecticut
  - Warburg (?) (Box 6, Folder 35)
  - Warren, Samuel (Box 6, Folder 36-39)
    Photos by Edith Hastings Tracy
  - Warren, Sylvia (Box 6, Folder 40)
  - Webber, Oscar (Box 6, Folder 41)
  - Weld, Margaret W. (Box 6, Folder 42-43)
    Location: Stamford, Connecticut
  - West, Arthur L. (Box 6, Folder 44)
    Location: Tallahassee, Florida
  - White, Windsor (Box 6, Folder 45-52)
    Photos by Tebbs and Kneel
  - White, Windsor (Box 17)
    Photos by Carol Betsch
  - Whittemore, Gertrude (Box 6, Folder 53)
  - Williams, Clark (Box 6, Folder 54-55)
  - Williams, Joseph (Box 6, Folder 56)
    Location: Cobb County, Georgia
  - Wilson, E.V.K. (Box 6, Folder 57)
  - Botanical Borders (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
  - H Miscellaneous (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - H Miscellaneous (Box 7, Folder 4)
    Identified as Thimble Farm
  - M Miscellaneous (Box 7, Folder 5-7)
  - P Miscellaneous (Box 7, Folder 8)
    Natchez
  - P Miscellaneous (Box 7, Folder 9)
    Rosedown
  - P Miscellaneous (Box 7, Folder 10)
    Uncle Sam's
  - P Miscellaneous (Box 7, Folder 11)
    Weeks Hall
  - Plantations (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - S Miscellaneous (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Unidentified (Box 7, Folder 14-23)
  - Louis Allen (Box 12, Folder 1-2)
  - Robert Brothers (Box 12, Folder 3-4)
  - Erkins Studio (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Joseph C. Fleri (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - George Funk (Box 12, Folder 7-8)
  - Garden Figures (Box 12, Folder 9-13)
  - Garden Ornaments (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Francis Grimes (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Richard Lehne - Antiques (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Richard Lehne (Box 13, Folder 3-5)
  - Edward McCarten - Figures (Diana) (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Monuments (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Victory Garden and Home Defense Kitchen (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Four Seasons (framed) (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Herbert Adams (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Louis Allen - Fountains (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Erkins Studios (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Garden Figures - miscellaneous (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Richard Lehne - antiques (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Victory Garden and Defense Kitchen (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - George Funk Antiques (Box 13, Folder 16)
- Series II. Correspondence and Accounts
  - Hanna, Pamela H.- note, Undated (Box 8, Folder 0)
  - Mother and Daughters Club, September 8, 1931 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Prizes awarded for gardens, 1928-1938 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Auditor, 1941-1944 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Brook Place Vouchers and Record of Timber Sales, 1942-1945 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Charity, 1943 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Vouchers, 1944 (Box 8, Folder 5-6)
  - I-K; Insurance, 1944, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    Includes correspondence with Knox
  - Bills A-C, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Bills D-W, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Beekman Place, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Bermuda, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Brook Place, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Conoley, Douglas, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Curry, Mrs. Henry M., Jr., 1945 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Dodge, Henry M. - Bills, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - E.S. Florida correspondence, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Hanes, James, Ralph and Jordon, P.H., 1945 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Laurel, Mississippi, 1944-1945 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Office Miscellaneous, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Orders - Plant, seed, and shrub, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Secor, George Barnes, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Stern, Edgar B., 1945 (Box 8, Folder 22)
    see also Box 8, Folder 58
  - Stillwell, Mrs. Edward, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 23)
    see also Box 8, Folder 59
  - Stranahan, Duane, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Truesdale, M.D., 1945 (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - Tucker, Carll, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - A-B Miscellaneous, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - C Miscellaneous, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - Marjorie Knox and Mrs. Hazard Campbell, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 28A)
  - D-G Miscellaneous, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 29)
  - H Miscellaneous, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 30)
  - Re: Ingalls; Re: King; Re: Knox, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 31)
  - L-M Miscellaneous, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 32)
  - N Miscellaneous, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 33)
    Primarily Neff
  - O-S Miscellaneous, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 34)
  - U-Z Miscellaneous, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 35)
  - Auditor Accountant, 1945-1946 (Box 8, Folder 36)
  - Bedford property, 1946 (Box 8, Folder 37)
  - Beekman Place, 1946 (Box 8, Folder 38)
  - Bermuda, 1946 (Box 8, Folder 39)
  - Brook Place, 1946 (Box 8, Folder 40)
  - Chatham, Mrs. Thurman, 1946 (Box 8, Folder 41)
  - Corn Exchange Bank, 1946 (Box 8, Folder 42)
  - Curry, Mrs. Henry M., Jr., 1946 (Box 8, Folder 43)
  - Dodge, Henry M., 1946 (Box 8, Folder 44)
  - Floyd, Ruth E. (Mr. Orcutt), 1946 (Box 8, Folder 45)
  - Gardeners, Contractors, etc., 1945-1946 (Box 8, Folder 46)
  - Goldman Sachs Material, 1946 (Box 8, Folder 47)
  - Gray, Gordon, 1946 (Box 8, Folder 48)
  - Guaranty Trust Company, New York, 1946 (Box 8, Folder 49)
  - Hanes, Ralph, Gordon, and Philip, 1946 (Box 8, Folder 50)
  - Houghton, 1946 (Box 8, Folder 51)
  - Interior Decorating Notes, 1945-1946 (Box 8, Folder 52)
  - Lectures, 1945-1946 (Box 8, Folder 53)
  - Mather, William G., 1946 (Box 8, Folder 54)
  - Office - Miscellaneous, 1946 (Box 8, Folder 55)
  - Orders for plant and seed, 1946 (Box 8, Folder 56)
  - Secor, George Barnes, 1946 (Box 8, Folder 57)
  - Stern, Edgar B., 1946 (Box 8, Folder 58)
  - Stillwell, Mrs. Edward C., 1946 (Box 8, Folder 59)
  - Truesdale, M.D., 1946 (Box 8, Folder 60)
  - Tucker, Mrs. Carll, 1946 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Vermont Savings Bank, 1946 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Von Kettler, Baroness Maud, 1946 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - A-B Miscellaneous, 1946 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - C Miscellaneous, 1946 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - D Miscellaneous, 1946 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - E-F Miscellaneous, 1946 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - G-H Miscellaneous, 1946 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - I-K Miscellaneous, 1946 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - L-N Miscellaneous, 1946 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - O-Q Miscellaneous, 1946 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - R Miscellaneous, 1946 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - S Miscellaneous, 1946 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - T-Z Miscellaneous, 1946 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Brook Place Bills, 1946 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Charity, 1946 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Insurance, 1946 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - A-B Bills, 1946 (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - C-M Bills, 1946 (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - N-W Bills, 1946 (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Arboretum Bulletins, 1936-1941 (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Arboretum Bulletins, 1917, 1936-1942 (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Architectural Design (articles) (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Burke, E.S., Jr. (article) (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Beekman Hall, undated (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - Campbell House (notes), undated (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - "Chatham", 1932 and 1938 (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - Construction (general), 1939 (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - T. Crowther and Son - Antiquity London, undated (Box 9, Folder 27)
  - Fencing - DuBois (and others), 1931 and 1945 (Box 9, Folder 28)
  - Fencing - Reeves, 1937 and 1938 (Box 9, Folder 29)
  - Fireplaces (outdoors), undated (Box 9, Folder 30)
  - Flower Pots (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Garden Furniture, undated (Box 9, Folder 31)
    W.A. Snow Iron Works, Inc., and North Shore Ferneries Co.
  - Garden Notes, undated (Box 9, Folder 32)
  - Garden Photography (Notes), 1931 and 1935 (Box 9, Folder 33)
  - Hardware, 1926-1928 and 1930 (Box 9, Folder 34)
  - Hodgson Houses, 1937 and 1940 (Box 9, Folder 35)
  - Lawn Care, 1928, 1931, 1932, and 1935-1940 (Box 9, Folder 36)
  - Lead, 1929, 1931, 1932, and 1937 (Box 9, Folder 37)
  - Lighting, 1936 and 1938 (Box 9, Folder 38)
  - McKissick Gardens (Plants List), 1940 (Box 9, Folder 39)
  - National Sculpture Society (Catalogue of Exhibitions), 1940 (Box 9, Folder 40)
- Series III. Articles, Manuscripts, and Printed Materials
  Includes some correspondence
  - General
    - Paths - specification for earth, tanbark pine needle (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Perennials - notes (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Planting and care of biennials (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Plants and care of plants - miscellaneous (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Play areas (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Roads and swimming pools - specifications (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Mrs. Shipman's photograph and publicity (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Sketches (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Tiles (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Building material - bricks, shingles (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Soil preparation (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Swimming pools (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Sun dial data - 19 Beekman Place (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Tennis Courts and swimming pools (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Tucker, Carll - article (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - Wheeler, Williams, N.A. (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - Colonial woodwork details (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - Manuscript for preface and introduction to "Garden Note Book" by Ellen Shipman (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Notes and Drafts for an Unpublished Book
    - Notes for Ellen Shipman's Book (1), 1936-1937, 1945, undated (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Notes for Ellen Shipman's Book (2), Undated (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - Notes for Ellen Shipman's Book (3), Undated (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - Garden Note Book, 1938, undated (Box 18, Folder 4)
      Drafts of Preface
    - "Planting the Place" - drafts., Undated (Box 18, Folder 5)
      Also referred to as "Planting Your Place"
    - Planting - uncompleted, Undated (Box 18, Folder 6)
      Lists and descriptions of plants for various places in the garden
      (i.e. borders, ground covers, shade.)
    - Miscellaneous Notes, 1938, undated (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - "Design" manuscript, Undated (Box 18, Folder 8)
    - Color Combination Lecture, c. 1935 (Box 18, Folder 9)
    - Construction - Originals, 1931, undated (Box 18, Folder 10)
    - Planting, Undated (Box 18, Folder 11)
    - Construction -New, Undated (Box 18, Folder 12)
  - Posters
    - 2 Broadsides from "American Gardens and Landscapes on Paper 1790-1984" (Map-case Folder 196)
    - 1 Broadside "A Half Century of Garden Design", 1986 (Map-case Folder 196)
    - American Society of Landscape Architects meeting flyer, 1986 (Map-case Folder 196)
    - Title Poster for "The Gardens of Ellen Shipman Exhibit" (Map-case Item 1)
- Series IV. Project Files (Plans)
  - Arranged by Client - (Kept in original order, mainly alpha by client's last name. 2nd alpha sequence starts with Mapcase Folder 178.)
  - Mr. Herbert Adams (Map-case Folder 1)
    - Details of fence and gate by Charles A. Platt, architect, 1906 (Map-case Folder 1)
  - Mrs. Montgomery Angell (Map-case Folder 1)
    Location: Garrison, New York
    - Construction details for wooden fence (Blueprint), 1937 (Map-case Folder 1)
  - Alger Museum (Map-case Folder 1)
    - Dimensioned details of flower beds, 1937 (Map-case Folder 1)
    - Design plan for knot garden (x2), 1937 (Map-case Folder 1)
    - Plan for location of trees in Knot Garden, 1937 (Map-case Folder 1)
    - Revised design for Knot Garden (x2), 1937 (Map-case Folder 1)
  - Mrs. Russell Alger (Map-case Folder 1-5)
    - General garden layout plan, 1937 (Map-case Folder 1)
    - Tree and vine planting plan on last terrace, 1937 (Map-case Folder 1)
    - First floor plan - House (Blueprint), 1937 (Map-case Folder 1)
    - Construction plan for entrance drive, 1937 (Map-case Folder 1)
    - Details of swimming pool (Blueprints), 1937 (Map-case Folder 1)
    - Border plan of fruit trees and shrubs, 1937 (Map-case Folder 1)
    - Design plan for bamboo rose trellis, 1937 (Map-case Folder 1)
    - Construction plan for retaining wall along drive, 1937 (Map-case Folder 1)
    - Section through fountain and pool on East Terrace, 1937 (Map-case Folder 2)
    - Plan of fountain and pool on East Terrace, 1937 (Map-case Folder 2)
    - Construction plan for rose trellis, 1937 (Map-case Folder 2)
    - Tree and vine planting on West Terrace, 1937 (Map-case Folder 2)
    - Plan of garage court, 1937 (Map-case Folder 2)
    - Construction drawing for brick paving at ends of Bowling Green, 1937 (Map-case Folder 2)
    - Blub planting plan for East Terrace, 1937 (Map-case Folder 2)
    - Blub planting plan for West Terrace, 1937 (Map-case Folder 2)
    - Perennial planting plan for West Terrace, 1937 (Map-case Folder 2)
    - Perennial planting plan for East Terrace, 1937 (Map-case Folder 2)